<appendix id="dedicationap">
<title>Personal Dedication</title>

<para>
There are so many people I could thank.  I will name here but a few
of the people who have brought me to where I am today.  The many family
members, Sunday School teachers, youth pastors, school teachers, friends,
and other relationships that God has brought into my life to lead me, help
me, and teach me are too many to count.  This book is dedicated to you all.
</para>

<para>
There are some people, however, that I would like to thank specifically.
</para>

<para>
First of all, I want to thank the members of the Vineyard Christian Fellowship 
Church in Champaign, Illinois for everything that you have done to help me and my 
family in our times of crisis.  It's been a long time since I've seen or 
heard from any of you, but I think about you always.  You have been
such a blessing to me, my wife, and Daniel, and I could never thank you
enough for showing us Christ's love when we needed it most.  I thank God
every time I think of you - I thank Him for bringing you all to us in
our deepest times of need.  Even out in the middle of Illinois with no
friends of family, God showed that He was still watching after us.  Thank
you for being His hands on Earth.  Specifically, I'd like to thank Joe and 
Rhonda, Pam and Dell, and Herschel and Vicki.  There were many, many others, 
too - so many people helped us that it would be impossible to list them all.
</para>

<para>
I also want to thank my parents, who gave me the example of perserverance and
strength in hard times.  Your example has helped me be a good father to my
children, and a good husband to my wife.
</para>

<para>
I also want to thank my wife, who even from when we first started dating encouraged
me to seek God in everything.  Thank you for your support in writing this book,
and more importantly, for your support in being obedient to God.
</para>

<para>
I also want to thanks the Little Light House school.  
My entire family is continually blessed by the help you give to our
son.
</para>

<para>
I also want to thank Joe and D.A.  Thank you for taking a chance on me
in ministry.  Being able to be a part of God's ministry again has helped me
in so many ways.
</para>

<para>
You all have given me the strength I needed to write this book over the last
few years.  Without your support, I would have been too overwhelmed by personal
crises to even think about anything more than getting through a day, much less
putting this book together.  You have all been a great
blessing to me, and I will keep you in my prayers always.
</para>

<!--
<para>
This book has been in the making for a long time.  It started several years ago
when I was manager of Internet Systems Development at Wolfram Research.
As part of my job I interviewed candidates for positions.  I noticed that
the near-universal trait of qualified candidates was that they all knew 
assembly language.  Few were experts and even fewer used it regularly, but
everyone who knew assembly language had a deeper understanding of programming
issues than the other candidates.
</para>

<para>
Assembly language has long fallen out of vogue in education, and I believe
that this is causing the current generation of programmers to have a much
weaker foundation.   Assembly language was being viewed as an optional add-on 
that was only useful for operating-system programmers.  I wrote this book
to bring assembly language to the forefront of programmer education.
</para>

-->
</appendix>
